{"tossups": [{"question": "This man\u2019s associate, Elbert A. Woodward, committed both larceny and forgery while en route to a Connecticut Senate seat. Future presidential candidate Samuel Tilden refused to let this political figure free from prison even after he testified to the Alderman Committee. This man and his New York cronies were depicted as vultures in a <em>Harper\u2019s</em> <em>Weekly</em> political cartoon by Thomas Nast. For ten points, name this \u201cBoss\u201d of the political machine, Tammany Hall.", "answer": "William \u201cBoss\u201d <b><u>Tweed</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The oldest-known civilization to have been located in this region was the coastal, fishing-based Chinchorro Culture. This region is home to the world's largest open pit copper mine, Chuquicamata [[choo-kee-kah-MAH-tah]]. In 2003, this region was used by NASA to test its <em>Viking</em> landers due to its similarity to the surface of Mars. This region is believed to have been arid for at least three million years, making it the world's oldest desert. For ten points, name this extremely arid Chilean desert, which prior to 2015 had not seen precipitation for over 500 years.", "answer": "<b><u>Atacama</u></b> Desert (do not accept or prompt on \"Peru,\" \"Chile,\" or \"South America\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One of the most lopsided results of this process was led by the slogan \u201cYes, we love this land,\" which is also the title of the anthem of Norway, which underwent this process in 1905. Another one of these was defeated by the \u201cNo Thanks\u201d campaign, which countered the efforts of Alex Salmond and Nicola Sturgeon. An illegal one of these in Spain was preceded by multiple human chains and was followed by the arrest of the president of Catalonia. For ten points, name this democratic process, which sometimes results in new countries.", "answer": "<b><u>Independence referendum</u></b>s (or <b><u>independence referenda</u></b>; accept <b><u>plebiscite</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>referendum(a)</u></b>; accept <b><u>vote</u></b> for <b><u>independence</u></b> and similar answers)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This composer was the grandson of a philosopher who inspired the <em>Haskalah</em>. This composer's <em>Festgesang</em> [[FEST-ge-SAHNG]] was adapted into the Christmas Carol \"Hark! The Herald Angels Sing.\" During a trip to the United Kingdom, this composer's visit to Fingal's Cave inspired his Hebrides [[HEH-brih-dees]] Overture. This composer collected eight volumes of six Lieder [[LEE-deh]] in his <em>Songs Without Words</em>. For ten points, name this Jewish-German composer who wrote the incidental music for <em>A Midsummer Night\u2019s</em> <em>Dream</em>.", "answer": "Felix <b><u>Mendelssohn</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In support of freedom fighters in this war, U.S. folk group the Almanac Singers, led by activist Pete Seeger, wrote an album of songs such as \"Jarama Valley\" from a U.S. battalion which fought in this war. The use of manufacturing plants in Nazi Germany allowed American companies like GM and Ford to provide twelve thousand vehicles to Falangist [[fah-LAHN-jist]] forces during this intranational war. The Neutrality Act of 1935 prevented the U.S. from intervening in, for ten points, what war between the Republicans and Fascists led by Francisco Franco?", "answer": "<b><u>Spanish Civil</u></b> War (or Guerra <b><u>Civil Espa\u00f1ola</u></b>; accept <b><u>Civil</u></b> War in <b><u>Spain</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "These people failed to overwhelm European forces who were using the <em>laager</em>, or wagon fort, strategy during the Battle of Blood River. Conquests by these people led to the <em>Mfecane</em> [[MM-feh-KAH-nee]], or \u201cthe Crushing,\u201d a period of mass migration of Nguni [[nn-GOO-nee]] people. These people often pincered their opponents using the \"Horn of the Buffalo\u201d formation, implemented by their <em>impi</em> regiments. For ten points, name this Southern African people, once led by King Shaka.", "answer": "<b><u>Zulu</u></b> people (or ama<b><u>Zulu</u></b>; accept <b><u>Zulu</u></b> Kingdom; accept <b><u>Zulu</u></b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This author's alleged incestuous relationship with his half-sister may have resulted in the birth of Elizabeth Medora Leigh. This author's only legitimate child was the early computer scientist Ada Lovelace. This author was described as \"mad, bad, and dangerous to know\" by his mistress Lady Caroline Lamb. This author died of sepsis before he could help attack the Ottoman fortress of Lepanto during the Greek War for Independence. For ten points, name this Romantic poet, the author of \"She Walks in Beauty.\"", "answer": "Lord <b><u>Byron</u></b> (or George <b><u>Gordon</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s raid on Fort Brooke coincided with his ally Micanopy\u2019s [[mih-CAN-oh-pees]] ambush of Francis Dade\u2019s U.S. army regiment. General Thomas Jesup captured this leader under a false \u201cwhite flag\u201d truce, and the poor conditions at Fort Moultrie led to this man's death. This chief orchestrated the breaking of the Treaty of Payne\u2019s Landing, beginning a second conflict between his tribe and the U.S. army. For ten points, name this Florida chief, the primary Native American leader during the Second Seminole War.", "answer": "<b><u>Osceola</u></b> (or <b><u>Asi-yahola</u></b>; accept Billy <b><u>Powell</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As HUD Secretary, this man urged Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac to buy loans from poor home owners, possibly causing the subprime mortgage crisis. This man noted that George Pataki \"held the leader's coat\" and that \"Cream rises to the top,\" referring to Rudy Giuliani. This man sued Rhode Island over its Quarantine policy, despite having his own lockdown policy. This man faces allegations of sexual harassment and admitted to covering up COVID-19 deaths at nursing homes. For ten points, name this governor of New York.", "answer": "<b><u>A</u></b>ndrew <b><u>Cuomo</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This organization attempted to exile the author of <em>My Country and the World</em> before he could earn his 1975 Nobel Peace Prize. The head of this organization, Vladimir Kryuchkov, helped lead a 1991 coup to stop the presidential reforms of a man who was championed by a former head of this organization, Yuri Andropov. The NKVD served as the predecessor of this organization, and Russian president Vladimir Putin served as an agent for this organization in the late 1980s. For ten points, name this Soviet equivalent to the CIA.", "answer": "<b><u>KGB</u></b> (accept <b><u>Committee for State Security</u></b>; or <b><u>Komitet Gosudarstvennoy</u></b> <b><u>Bezopasnosti</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "J\u00e1come Ratton [[JAH-kohm rah-TOHN]] wrote scathing attacks on this country. An anti-seismic building system from this country features <em>gaiola</em> [[gai-OH-lah]] cages developed after a 1755 event. This country curbed Jesuit power in the T\u00e1vora Affair, razing noble lands at the \"alley of the salted ground.\" One of history's first restraining orders was issued in this country against the Marquis of Pombal. Signing the Methuen [[meh-THOO-en]] Treaty with England, for ten points, what is this country, the site of the Great Lisbon earthquake?", "answer": "<b><u>Portugal</u></b> (accept <b><u>Portuguese</u></b> Republic; accept Rep\u00fablica <b><u>Portuguesa</u></b>; accept <b><u>Portuguese</u></b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1993, an expert in this activity named Nigel Short created the PCA after cutting ties with an international organization. One man refused to participate in a 1975 World Championship in this activity because he espoused a first-to-ten wins schedule rather than a first-to-five wins schedule. In 1972, this event\u2019s championship was held in Iceland and billed as a contest between the U.S. and the U.S.S.R., because it pitted Boris Spassky against Bobby Fischer. For ten points, name this game, whose leading grandmasters include Fabiano Caruana and Magnus Carlsen.", "answer": "<b><u>Chess</u> </b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "The killing of three settlers by this tribe in the town of Cascade led to U.S. army skirmishes during the Sheepeater War. William Clark nicknamed a child from this tribe \"Pompey\" and took care of him after his mother\u2019s death. A member of this tribe, whose leaders included Pocatello, was married to French-Canadian trader Toussaint Charbonneau [[SHAR-ben-no]] and successfully traveled through the Bozeman Pass while serving as a guide with the Corps of Discovery. For ten points, name this Idaho tribe, whose members have included Sacagawea.", "answer": "<b><u>Shoshone</u></b> (or <b><u>Shoshoni</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this event, eleven detainees at a colonial detention camp were clubbed to death by guards in the Hola Massacre. In 1952, Governor Evelyn [[EEV-lin]] Baring declared a state of emergency and ordered the imprisonment of Jomo Kenyatta and other rebel leaders in an attempt to prevent this event from occurring. Dedan Kimathi was executed in 1957 after leading an army during this event. For ten points, name this event, an armed struggle between the Kenya Land and Freedom Army and the British authorities.", "answer": "<b><u>Mau Mau</u></b> Uprising (accept \"Rebellion\" or \"Revolt\" in place of \"Uprising\"; accept <b><u>Kenya Emergency</u></b> before \"Kenyatta\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "John Husband set this song to \"Hephzibah\" [[HEP-zeh-bah]], while William Walker set this song to the \"New Britain\" tune using shape notes. The wretchedness discussed in this song may represent writer John Newton's realization of his wickedness as a slave trader. This song was published in <em>Olney Hymns</em> and was often used by Baptist ministers in the South during the Second Great Awakening. For ten points, name this Christian hymn whose opening line says that the title entity \"saved a wretch like me.\"", "answer": "<b><u>\"Amazing Grace\"</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "Gaston Means claimed this man's \"strange death\" resulted from poisoning, not a cerebral hemorrhage or cardiac arrest. In 1923, Charles R. Forbes, who served as director of the Veterans' Bureau in this man's administration, was indicted for fraud, just one of many scandals involving this man. This man had extramarital affairs with Nan Britton and Carrie Fulton Phillips. For ten points, name this U.S. president whose involvement in the Teapot Dome scandal came to light only after he died in office.", "answer": "Warren Gamaliel <b><u>Harding</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This figure took inspiration from the writings of anarchist and fellow countryman Ricardo Flores Mag\u00f3n to adopt the slogan \"Tierra y Libertad.\" Under the guise of a meeting, Jes\u00fas Guajardo [[gwah-HAR-doh]] assassinated this resident of Morelos state in 1919 on the orders of Venustiano Carranza. This man, who met with Pancho Villa at the Aguascalientes Convention of 1914, led the Liberation Army of the South against the government of Francisco Madero. For ten points, name this agrarian revolutionary during the Mexican Revolution.", "answer": "Emiliano <b><u>Zapata</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This country was the location of the Cassette Scandal in which Leonid Kuchma [[KOOCH-mah]] was implicated in the kidnapping of a journalist. The Pora! Youth demonstrated in this country in the Orange Revolution, which led to the presidency of Viktor Yushchenko [[yoosh-CHEN-koh]]. Starting in 2014, this country faced separatists in the Donbass and Donetsk People's Republic, and its lands in the Crimean Peninsula were annexed by Vladimir Putin. For ten points, name this neighbor of Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>Ukraine</u> </b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Massachusetts city where they led protests against a 1770 massacre", "answer": "<b><u>Boston</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Commodity that they threw into the harbor during a 1773 event in that city", "answer": "<b><u>Tea</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Cousin of a future U.S. president who founded the organization", "answer": "<b><u>S</u></b>amuel <b><u>Adams</u></b> (prompt on \"Adams\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "1765 tax on printed materials whose repeal led the original Sons of Liberty to disband", "answer": "<b><u>Stamp</u></b> Act", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "British official responsible for implementing that act who was hanged in effigy from the Liberty Tree", "answer": "Andrew <b><u>Oliver</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Ship boarded by John Brown which ran aground while pursuing the <em>Hannah</em>", "answer": "HMS <em><b><u>Gaspee</u> </b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Tailor and spy who used his slave Cato to send secret information during the Revolution", "answer": "Hercules <b><u>Mulligan</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Customs official who was tarred and feathered after a dispute with George Hewes", "answer": "John <b><u>Malcom</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Sovereign country she led from London", "answer": "<b><u>U</u></b>nited <b><u>K</u></b>ingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (accept <b><u>Britain</u></b>; accept <b><u>Great Britain</u></b>; prompt on \"England,\" \"Scotland,\" \"Wales,\" or \"Northern Ireland\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Irish independence organization that attempted to kill her at Brighton", "answer": "Provisional <b><u>Irish Republican Army</u></b> (accept <b><u>IRA</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Archipelago she invaded after it was seized by Argentina", "answer": "<b><u>Falkland</u></b> Islands (accept <b><u>Falklands</u></b>; accept Islas <b><u>Malvinas</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Shakespeare-inspired term for a period of strikes that led to her becoming PM", "answer": "<b><u>Winter of Discontent</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "President of the United Mine Workers who led an 1984-85 strike against her government", "answer": "Arthur <b><u>Scargill</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Former PM she defeated in 1975 to become leader of the Conservative party", "answer": "Edward <b><u>Heath</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Controversial tax imposed on Scotland that was replaced by the Council Tax", "answer": "<b><u>Community Charge</u></b> (accept <b><u>poll tax</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Secretary of State for the Environment who seized control of the Conservative party from Thatcher in 1990", "answer": "Michael <b><u>Heseltine</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Pirate who owned <em>Queen Anne's Revenge</em>, known for putting lit fuses in his facial hair", "answer": "<b><u>Blackbeard</u></b> (accept Edward <b><u>Teach</u></b>; accept Edward <b><u>Thatch</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Pirate who hid stolen goods at Gardiners Island leading to the legend of his buried treasure", "answer": "Captain William <b><u>Kidd</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "Privateer and governor of Jamaica who lends his name to a popular brand of rum.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Morgan</u></b> (accept Captain <b><u>Morgan</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Nine-letter word for certain privateers, taken from the Arawak word for a wooden frame on which they roasted manatees", "answer": "<b><u>Buccaneer</u></b>s", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Jamaican city that served as a hub for piracy until it was destroyed by a 1692 earthquake", "answer": "<b><u>Port Royal</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Partner of Calico Jack Rackham and Mary Read who stayed her execution due to being pregnant", "answer": "Anne <b><u>Bonny</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "Adjective given to a series of \"abductions\" in 1627 in which pirates from Algiers took people from Iceland and sold them into slavery", "answer": "<b><u>Turkish</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Most successful pirate, a Welshman who captured more than 470 vessels", "answer": "<b><u>Black Bart</u></b> (accept Bartholomew <b><u>Roberts</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The first capture of a foreign ship by a U.S. Navy vessel occurred during this</u></b> <b><u>conflict, when the USS</u> </b><em><b><u>Delaware</u></b></em><b><u> trapped the privateering vessel</u> </b><em><b><u>La Croyable</u></b></em><b><u> [[kroi-</u><u>YAH-bluh]] in Great Egg Harbor. The massive bribes requested to meet (+)</u> Talleyrand during the XYZ Affair led to this conflict. The Convention of 1800, hosted by Consul (*) </b>Napoleon Bonaparte, ended this two-year conflict and affirmed U.S. neutrality. For ten points, name this undeclared naval war between the United States and France during John Adams\u2019s Presidency.", "answer": "<b><u>Quasi</u></b>-War (prompt on \"War of the Second Coalition\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A fantasia for piano titled</u> </b><em><b><u>Agonia e morte di [this man]</u></b></em><b><u> was written by Franz</u></b> <b><u>Xaver S\u00fcssmayr [[SOOS-my-er]] who was also recruited to finish another work by this</u></b> <b><u>man in 1791. Georg Fredrich Daumer claimed that this composer was murdered by</u></b> <b><u>freemasons for revealing their secrets in an opera in which the (+)</u> Queen of the Night enlists Tamino to save her daughter. This composer's life was depicted in a namesake film directed by (*) </b>Milo\u0161 [[MEE-loash]] Forman. For ten points, name this Austrian composer of <em>The Magic Flute</em>.", "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus <b><u>Mozart</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>116 out of 156 of these things were destroyed in Operation Deadlight while</u></b> <b><u>most of the rest were claimed as prizes or sold. The earliest of these things was</u></b> <b><u>Wilhelm Bauer's</u> </b><em><b><u>Brandtaucher</u></b></em><b><u>, and during the Battle of the (+)</u> Atlantic, Karl D\u00f6nitz [[DEHR-nitz]] developed the \u201cwolf pack\u201d strategy with these things. This type of vessel (*) </b>torpedoed the RMS <em>Lusitania</em>, turning American opinion against the Central Powers during World War One. The Germans conducted \u201cunrestricted submarine warfare\u201d with, for ten points, which naval vessels?", "answer": "<b><u>U-Boat</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Unterseeboot</u></b>en; prompt on \u201csubmarine\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man was banned from sports at Columbia University after he used the</u></b> <b><u>assumed name Henry Lewis to play professionally. Mayor Fiorello La Guardia</u></b> <b><u>appointed this man parole commissioner of New York in the last year of his life. This</u></b> <b><u>man was the first living person to appear on a (+)</u> Wheaties box and the first MLB player to have his number retired. This man claimed to be \"the luckiest (*) </b>man on the face of the earth\" in his retirement speech to a packed stadium in New York. For ten points, name this Yankees first baseman who died from a namesake neuromuscular disease.", "answer": "Lou <b><u>Gehrig</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>Orders by this man led to the murder of translator Hitoshi Igarashi. Nader</u></b> <b><u>Naderpour often recited poetry with this man whose disciple, Morteza Motahhari,</u></b> <b><u>founded the Combatant Clergy Association. This man's opposition to the White</u></b> <b><u>Revolution led the (*)</u> Shah to send troops to Qom [[GOHM]], and this man's house arrest led to the 15 Khordad Uprising. This man regularly called the U.S. the \"Great Satan\" and published a </b><em><b>fatwa</b></em><b> calling for (*) </b>Salman Rushdie's murder. Having gained national popularity through the Iran Hostage Crisis, for ten points, who was this Ayatollah?", "answer": "Ayatollah Ruhollah <b><u>Khomeini</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>With help from Lawrence J. Spagnola, this man wrote an autobiography</u></b> <b><u>subtitled</u> </b><em><b><u>My Journey from Rebellion to Redemption</u></b></em><b><u>. The Christopher Commission was</u></b> <b><u>formed after an attack on this man who, in a televised address, repeated the phrase</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> \"We've got to quit\" after asking the question, \"Can we all get along?\" George Holliday recorded Stacey Koon and three other individuals (*) </b>beating this man in the aftermath of a high-speed chase. For ten points, name this man whose beating by the LA Police Department led to a series of 1992 riots in Los Angeles.", "answer": "Rodney <b><u>King</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This son of a former Ambassador to Hungary facilitated the rearmament of</u></b> <b><u>Israel with Iron Dome Surface-to-Air Missiles during the 2014 Gaza conflict. On his</u></b> <b><u>first day in office, this Cabinet member froze all arms sales to (+)</u> Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates. During his confirmation hearing, this politician promised to continue recognition of (*) </b>Jerusalem as the capital of Israel rather than returning the U.S. embassy to Tel Aviv. For ten points, name this Secretary of State in the Biden administration.", "answer": "Antony <b><u>Blinken</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This left-wing figure used the pseudonym \"Gunnar Gaasland\" while living in</u></b> <b><u>Norway until the rise of the Quisling government. This head of the SPD resigned after</u></b> <b><u>his aide, G\u00fcnter Guillaume [[gee-YOHM]], was outed as a secret agent for the (*)</u> </b><em><b>Stasi </b></em><b>[[SHTAH-see]]. This chancellor collapsed weeping at the Warsaw Ghetto monument while on a state visit to Poland. This man won the 1971 Nobel (*) </b>Peace Prize for his work to strengthen European cooperation. For ten points, name this West German chancellor who pursued <em>Ostpolitik</em> while attempting to reconcile with East Germany.", "answer": "Willy <b><u>Brandt</u></b> (accept Herbert Ernst Karl <b><u>Frahm</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A poem in this man's voice proclaims he is \"the great dragon\u2026fear inspiring\u2026I</u></b> <b><u>am the young lion.\" Ishme-Dagan [[EESH-may dah-GAHN]] I and this man fought a war</u></b> <b><u>leading Mut-Ashkur to pay tribute to this man. Friedrich Delitzsch [[DAY-litch]] gave</u></b> <b><u>a lecture to the (+)</u> Kaiser on this man, a member of the Amorite Dynasty, a creation of whose was translated by Jean-Vincent Scheil [[SHILE]]. A (*) </b>stele [[STEE-lee]] in the shape of an index finger contains the rule \"an eye for an eye,\" part of this man's code. For ten points, name this Babylonian lawgiving king.", "answer": "<b><u>Hammurabi</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}